<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<primer3Doc version="1.0">
<textBlock>
	<id></id>
	<head></head>
	<text>
<![CDATA[ ]]>
	</text>
</textBlock>
<textBlock>
	<id>citationRequest</id>
	<head>How to cite primer3</head>
	<text>
<![CDATA[We request but do not require that use of this software be cited in
publications as

Steve Rozen and Helen J. Skaletsky (2000)
Primer3 on the WWW for general users and for biologist programmers.
In: Krawetz S, Misener S (eds)
Bioinformatics Methods and Protocols: Methods in Molecular Biology.
Humana Press, Totowa, NJ, pp 365-386

Source code available at http://primer3.sourceforge.net/
The paper above is available at
http://jura.wi.mit.edu/rozen/papers/rozen-and-skaletsky-2000-primer3.pdf]]>
	</text>
</textBlock>
<textBlock>
	<id>invokingPrimer3</id>
	<head>INVOKING primer3_core</head>
	<text>
<![CDATA[By default, the executable program produced by the Makefile is
called primer3_core.  This is the C program that does the heavy
lifting of primer picking.  There is also a more user-friendly
web interface (distributed separately).

The command line for primer3 can be:

primer3_core [ -format_output ] [ -strict_tags ] < input_file.txt

WARNING: primer3_core only reads its input on stdin, so the usual
unix convention of

primer3_core input_file.txt

*will not work*.  Primer3_core will just sit there forever
waiting for its input on stdin.]]>
	</text>
</textBlock>
<textBlock>
	<id>TagInputTpes</id>
	<head>Primer3 input tags</head>
	<text>
<![CDATA[There are 3 major classes of input tags.  "Sequence" input tags
starting with SEQUENCE_... describe a particular input sequence 
to primer3, and are reset after every boulder record.  "Global" 
input tags starting with PRIMER_... describe the general parameters 
that primer3 should use in its searches, and the values of these 
tags persist between input boulder records until or unless they 
are explicitly reset. The third class of P3_... tags describe 
parameters which modify the way primer3 provides the output (for 
example as separate files) and do not influence the primer selection 
itself.
Tags which do not start with SEQUENCE_, PRIMER_ or P3_ are ignored 
by primer3.
  Errors in "Sequence" input tags invalidate the current record, 
but primer3 will continue to process additional records.
  Errors in "Global" input tags are fatal because they invalidate 
the basic conditions under which primers are being picked.]]>
	</text>
</textBlock>
</primer3Doc>